[MUSIC]
控制型二錯誤率
In this lecture, we'll take a closer look
at controlling your Type 2 error rate.
這一講來談如何控制型二錯誤率
If you design a study and you're going to go through all the effort to collect data,
設計好一項研究，開始收集資料之前
you want to make sure that the probability that you'll find in effect
要估計能發現效果的機率
if it's actually there is high enough to make the data collection worthwhile.
確認機率高到值得收集資料
Now remember that the Type 2 error is a situation where you're saying that there's
型二錯誤是宣稱沒有效果
nothing, when there's actually something to be observed.
實際上效果存在的錯誤
So you're concluding that there's no support for
如果沒有足夠的檢定力
your hypothesis whereas if you would have enough statistical power,
就有無法下結果支持假設的結論
you would have said that there's actually a true effect.
無法肯定效果確實存在
Let's take a look at a classic question that's asked by Tversky and
就拿Tversky與Kahneman提出的經典問題來說
Kahneman where they find that people actually don't really know
他們發現研究者不會根據機率做出正確決策
what the probability is that a study will yield an informative answer.
They ask researchers to think about the following situation.
他們請研究者設想這樣的問題
It is "known" that the effect exists in a population.
假如"已知"母群中存在效果
So we're sampling from a situation where there is a true effect to be observed.
為此抽樣觀察估計是否確實存在
Then there's a pilot study where a difference was observed between two
已有前置研究發現兩筆資料間的差異
groups.
You have some statistics.
為確定差異做了統計
Sample size of 22 for example.
假如其中一筆有22個樣本
A mean and a standard deviation.
有平均數及標準差
And you have a second group with 23 people also a mean,
另一筆有23個樣本，平均數及標準差
that's a little bit higher and another standard deviation.
第二筆平均數比第一筆平均數高一些
Now you've observed the statistically significant effect in this pilot study.
跑了統計檢定發現前置研究有顯著效果
The p value is smaller than 0.05.
也就是p值小於0.05
The question that Tversky and Kahneman ask is let's say that you set out to repeat
Tversky和Kahneman以此設定提問一模一樣的研究
this study in exactly the same way, the same sample size and everything.
再做一次的話,會不會得到相同的統計值
What's now the probability that you'll observe
發現顯著效果的p值會是多少？
a statistically significant effect?
Take a moment to think about it.
暫停一下想一想
How would you answer this question?
你的答案是什麼？
What Tversky and
Tversky和Kahneman發現多數人回答有95%
的機會得到相同結果
Kahneman found is that most people say that there's a 95% probability.
Tversky和Kahneman發現多數人回答有95%
的機會得到相同結果
That a replication study will again give us statistically significant results.
也認為再做一次同樣有顯著結果
There seems to be some confusion in what the p value means.
這顯示p值似乎被誤解
Apparently, people take it as a indicating
作答者明顯把95%當成成功確認效果存在的機率
there's now 95% probable that's there is true effect.
And then, the following study will also observe this effect.
因此認為之後的再現研究能發現一樣的效果
But the correct answer is that you have to perform a power analysis.
正確答案是必須先做檢定力分析
In this graph we can see different curves that reflect the probability that we'll
這張圖的每條曲線代表特定的效果量
find a statistically significant effect if there is a true effect.
發現顯著結果的相對檢定力
So in other words, the statistical power
that we have is a function of the effect
檢定力是由效果量與樣本數所決定
size and the sample size.
The larger the sample size,
樣本數越大
the higher the probability that we'll find us statistically significant effect.
自然有更高的機會發現統計顯著結果
And the higher the effect size the more probable it is that we'll find this effect
另一方面，實際效果越大，越有可能從小樣本
even with smaller sample sizes.
發現顯著結果
So taking a look at these power graphs before you design a study is a useful way
設計研究前先參考這張圖
to think of the number of people that you might need when you
有助決定收集資料的最佳樣本數
perform a data collection.
Let's have one specific example.
來看一下這個例子
For example, you think you might examine an effect with a coenz
假設想證實的效果有0.5的效果量
d effect size of 0.5 which is considered a medium effect.
一般認為這是中等的效果量
Actually, in psychology if you throw all psychological resource in one big pile,
其實你把所有心理學文獻做大數據分析
the average effect size is around 0.43.
會發現平均效果量大約是0.43
So this is a slightly optimistic estimate but still possible.
所以這個研究設計是相當樂觀的
Now if you want to achieve 95% power in the study that you want to design,
如果期望研究設計有95%的檢定力
you actually need to collect 100 people in each condition in an independent
你需要兩組都收集100人
T-test to achieve this level of 95% power that you want to get.
獨立t檢定才符合95%的檢定力
So it's quite a substantial number of observations that you need to have a high
如此高的樣本數能確保存在效果的結論
有很高的機率可被成功再現
probability of concluding that there actually is an effect,
如此高的樣本數能確保存在效果的結論
有很高的機率可被成功再現
when there is a true effect.
如此高的樣本數能確保存在效果的結論
有很高的機率可被成功再現
So the Type 2 error rate in this case is only 0.5%.
這項研究的型二錯誤率因此被控制在5%
But getting it this low requires a large number of observations.
但是相對要付出的是需要大量的樣本
If you design under powered studies and you don't think of the number of people
如果你設計的研究沒有估計檢定力與樣本數
you need, for example, to have high statistical power,
研究結果以高檢定力的標準來看訊資量不多
then you're designing studies that have low informational value.
If you do not find an effect it's very difficult to say
而且若沒有發現任何顯著結果
that you didn't find an effect because there is no true effect.
很難說是因為效果實際上不存在
Or that you didn't find an effect because you didn't have enough observations
還是因為收集的樣本數不足
to have observed a statistically significant finding.
才沒有統計顯著結果
If you design a study with high power, and
如果想讓研究設計有高檢定力
thus with a low Type 2 error rate, you can consider these as severe tests.
以及低型二錯誤率，可以使用"嚴重度"分析
This is a very good test of you hypothesis.
這是一種良好的假設測試
If you really have a very high probability of finding an effect, if it's there.
如果你認為有很高的機率發現效果
So you have a very low Type 2 error, and you don't find an effect.
也有很低的型二錯誤率，研究結果卻毫無發現
Well, that something to make you wonder if there's really an effect or not.
這時也許會開始懷疑效果是不是真的存在
So you see that this is a very informational result.
這樣的發現提供有用的資訊
If you have very low power, you don't learn a lot.
如果檢定力太低，無法從結果學到新東西
So thinking about how to control your Type 2 errors is very important.
好好思考如何控制型二錯誤率是很重要的
In this case we have a P value
distribution of about 95% power and
這是設定95%檢定力所模擬的p值次數分配
you see that in this case you have a very severe test.
你可以看道這是極嚴格的測試
There is a true effect in our simulation.
這項模擬設定存在效果
We have 95% power so most of the time we will find a statistically significant
因為高檢定力使得多數p值低於顯著水準
只有極少的p值高於水準
result, it's very rare to find a higher P value
因為高檢定力使得多數p值低於顯著水準
只有極少的p值高於水準
most of the time if there is something there we will observe it.
因為高檢定力使得多數p值低於顯著水準
只有極少的p值高於水準
So, this is an example of a severe test situation where if we don't find a result,
不顯著的p值比例代表未發現效果的嚴重度
we should wonder if there's actually something to be observed.
讓我們能檢討有什麼問題導致無法發現
So, how can you increase your power?
那麼要如何增加檢定力呢？
There are several ways and the most attention is being given to increasing
最常用的辦法當然是直接增加樣本數
your sample size, that's of course a lot of work.
不過相當費工夫
It is a very good way to increase power.
雖然這是個好辦法
But that's not the only way.
卻非唯一的辦法
So let's discuss some alternative options.
來看看還有什麼方案
First of all, you can decrease the measurement error.
首先你可以減低測量誤差
This is a very important way of increasing
這種方法是從降低資料的變異下手
the statistical power that you have by reducing the variability in your data.
You can think about an IQ test.
拿IQ測驗為例
Instead of asking one question and then basing the IQ score on this one item.
不要用只問一題決定IQ分數的測驗
An IQ test has many items.
是用有很多題目的IQ測驗
Using this approach reduces measurement error and
這種測驗可以有效降低測量誤差
makes it easier to find differences between groups if they are really there.
也讓組間的差異容易被測量出來
The second approach that you can consider is using a within subject design.
第二種方案是採用參與者內設計
This increases the statistical power especially when the correlation between
不同條件的測量分數相關越高
the two measurements that you take is very high.
這種設計的考驗力也越高
In psychology this is very often the case.
心理學研究常使用這種設計
Think about a reaction time study where you have people respond to
尤其是反應時間的研究，像是比較刺激屬性
與反應屬性一致與否的Stroop效應
certain images or certain stimuli, that are either congruent or
尤其是反應時間的研究，像是比較刺激屬性
與反應屬性一致與否的Stroop效應
in congruent maybe a stroop test.
尤其是反應時間的研究，像是比較刺激屬性
與反應屬性一致與否的Stroop效應
We know that reaction times within an individual are very strongly correlated.
因為同一個人的反應時間在不同條件的
測量結果相關極高
So using it within design in this case increases the statistical
這類研究採參與者內設計會有很高的檢定力
power of observing an effect.
A third way that you can try is increasing the variability and the response options.
第三種方案是增加反應的多樣性或選項
This might make it easier to find differences if there's
反應選項多能增加發現差異的機會
enough variability in the data.
And you can think of the number
of items in a scale for example.
拿最常用的李克特量表來說
If you have a scale with only three or maybe five items, there's not a lot of
量表只有三或五個選項的話
wiggle room for people to vary on even if there's a real difference.
即使真有差異，受訪者也很難給出合適答案
If you have a large enough skill let's say seven items or nine items,
條件可行的話，建議用7到9個選項的量表
there's more possibility to have varying responses and
如此若真的有差異，比較容易測量出來
it's easier to find differences if there are really there.
Final way to consider is using a one sided test.
最後方案是採用單側檢定
If you have a directional prediction and you are not interested in effects that
如果假設有明確預期效果的增減方向
go in the opposite direction, then this is a good approach to
那麼這是確保有高考驗力的低成本方案
increase the statistical power without any additional costs.
People are not using these one sided tests as often as they should, but
雖然不是很多人常用的辦法
they are a very efficient way to collect high powered studies.
但是能有效保證起碼的統計檢定力
This is a graph illustrating the difference between a one sided test and
這張圖顯示果量是0.5的資料
單側t檢定與雙側t檢定的考驗力差異
a two sided test if we're examining a coenze d of 0.5 in a one sided t test.
這張圖顯示果量是0.5的資料
單側t檢定與雙側t檢定的考驗力差異
And you can see that with a one sided test you need about 26 people whereas
可以看到達到80%檢定力，單側t檢定需要26人
with a two sided test you would need about 34 people.
而雙側t檢定需要34人
So the difference might be small but if you have smaller effects it can become
如此條件發現的效果就算很小，也有很高的資訊量
quite substantial and it's just free if you have a directional prediction and
而且如果有效果方向的預測，能節省收集資料的成本
you specify this in advance before data collection.
Now there's some discussion in literature about which type of error is more severe.
型一還是型二錯誤那個比較嚴重有許多文獻探討
The Type 1 error where you say that there are something when there's
是你宣稱有效果，實際沒有的錯誤比較嚴重
actually nothing.
Or the Type 2 error when you say that there's nothing
是你宣稱沒有效果，實際有效果的錯誤比較嚴重
when there's actually something.
And it depends a little bit on how we organize our science.
這取決於每個人的科學觀點
As long as there are replications of results then Type 1 errors will be
任何研究的型一錯誤可經由他人的再現研究確認
identified if you try to replicate someone else's study and this was a Type 1 error.
It's very unlikely that you will find another Type 1 error.
如果無法再現就可確認真的是型一錯誤
The probability of doing this will substantially decrease,
因型一錯誤而發表的研究就會減少
it's very unlikely.
So as long as we replicate each other’s work enough sufficiently.
只要能充份再現已發表的研究
We will identify these Type 1 errors.
我們就能辨識因型一錯誤而產生的文獻
And you might say, well they don't impact the scientific literature too much.
也許你會說這類文獻的量並不多
In this case a Type 2 error might be much more severe.
也許有型二錯誤的文獻比較嚴重
If somebody tries out a new idea and
假定有人想出一個新點子
there is nothing there, other people might give up on this idea.
卻一無所獲，其他人就不會想嘗試這點子
So a Type 2 error might be more severe depending on whether we do enough control
型二錯誤的嚴重度取決於研究者的事前控制
and enough checking in a scientific literature to identify the Type 2 errors.
還有充分考察文獻裡的型二錯誤
As you see it's very important to control your Type 2 errors as well.
這一講討論各種控制型二錯誤的重要方法
People are very upset about Type 1 errors in the literature nowadays but
今天令多數研究者不愉快的情況是
多數文獻充斥型一錯誤
you can see that it might be even more severe to miss out on true fact
因為這類研究並未帶來有意義的知識
because your study did not have high enough informational value.
也許比沒發現真實效果更嚴重
You did not connect enough people to conclude that there is
沒有發現真實效果可能是收集的資料不夠多
an effect when there's actually a true effect.
So be sure that when you're designing your study,
記得在設計研究的時候
you evaluate the severity of the Type 1 error and the Type 2 error.
仔細衡量犯下型一與型二錯誤的嚴重度
And in certain situations it might be that a Type 2 error is much more severe and
某些時候，你應注意犯型二錯誤所付出的代價
it deserves your attention.
[MUSIC]
影片結束